Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Micki oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, March 16, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 114
    Micki is the Health and Safety Director of the CWA (Communications Workers of America) and lives in Queens, NY. Her role is to make sure workers are protected. On 9/11, she took a 6 AM flight to LaGuardia from Buffalo, NY and went directly to her office four blocks east of the WTC. At the time of the attack, she was on a city bus headed to a meeting when she heard someone say, “it’s a war—we’re under attack.” She could see the tower and smoke from the bus. She exited the bus and went into a court building, which was evacuated shortly after she entered. She found another bus and got on and tried to reach her husband on the phone. There were rumors on the bus—she reached her sister on the phone and her sister said the towers were gone. Micki was shocked and worried for her husband and for all the workers. Micki did not return to her office until the Monday after 9/11. She rode on a silent subway; the streets were white from the dust and deserted. Windows were broken and the towers were gone. The first few weeks were chaotic—communication was not good. The Verizon workers, part of CWA, were responsible for getting the Stock Exchange up and running. Questions were raised about dust, asbestos, etc. Health concerns were less in the beginning because of the tragedy of the event. Things changed rapidly, government agencies became involved: EPA, OSHA, etc., and deemed the air ok. Micki’s role was to determine if this information was accurate. The government agencies allowed companies to be less protective than they should have been—respirators were voluntary—there was no training and no fit testing. In early October, Micki went to Ground Zero to meet with the Verizon Health and Safety Director. Her role was to check on CWA members which include a large variety of workers—Verizon, Lucent, ATT, traffic enforcement, sanitation workers, nurses at NYU Hospital, Port Authority workers, and broadcast and engineer techs. Local union leadership dealt with many of the issues. Health and safety concerns changed to health concerns; there was much conflicting information. These concerns grew in October of 2001. Micki feels things are “still not being done with the way it should be done.” She spent time on and off the site over the next few months until mid-December. At the time, other 9/11 issues were raised—people asking if they could return to their offices, and Anthrax scares. Micki had to fight against the Bush Administration’s demand that workers get the smallpox vaccine (no purpose). Micki believes 9/11 continues to this day. There has never been an assessment of contamination in workplaces or residences surrounding Ground Zero. The issues were blatantly ignored—science was trusted to validate one viewpoint and has come back to haunt us. She battled the EPA. Senator Hillary Clinton got the EPA to set up an Expert Review Panel to review unmet health needs of workers and Micki was the liaison. The Panel did nothing and ended prematurely. She was angry, and still is. Politicians, i.e., Bush and Giuliani, said “go back to work and go shopping.” Micki feels we will never know the extent of health exposures due to financial interests. “It all happened again after Katrina and the Deep Water Horizon Spill.” Because issues have not been resolved, it provides Micki with motivation. “There needs to be a better formulation for a response from the government. The government does not take a pro-active approach.” Some positives were gained as a result of the event: Community advocates came together to fight issues and would do things differently in the future. There are still people suffering, so Micki cannot stop in her quest to create a safer workplace. 9/11 changed her life and how she views information from the government—she is much more cynical. Events are short-term but health is long-term. The needs of workers are important to do this kind of work—financial, physical and mental. “9/11 for each person will never end.” Micki hopes there is a willingness to do the right thing in the future.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Joseph oral history interview conducted by Andrew Flescher, March 21, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 115
    Joseph was a firefighter stationed in Midtown Manhattan in Fire Patrol #1. He lives in Lindenhurst on Long Island. While listening to the radio on the morning of 9/11, Joseph heard that an airplane had hit the World Trade Center. He jumped on the departing rig of the fire truck, as it left for the site, travelling the distance down Seventh Avenue. He could see the main fuselage of the plane sticking out of the WTC tower as they drove and ended up by the site at Broadway and Vesey streets. He waited with his company for instructions. After the second plane hit the other tower, he and the patrol received instructions to head in for rescue. As Joseph approached the building he saw a person fall to his death and land 10 feet away from him. Joseph then turned toward his lieutenant and stated that he did not think he could climb 60 flights of stairs during the rescue attempts. Joseph had been a carpenter before his firefighting career and he had the feeling that the buildings were going to collapse. He watched helplessly and prayed as he watched over 50 people jumped to their deaths. To this day Joseph experiences PTSD symptoms when he hears loud noises. All of the members of the patrol did not have enough time to deal with the situation, but tried as best as they could. They were given masks for protection but the intense smoke and fumes caused some of the men to regurgitate. Then the building started to collapse, as Joseph had thought it would. He talked about how one of his patrol buddies never made it out of the building; of how he thought he would never see his family again, although he did eventually manage to drive home to Lindenhurst. During the time he spent on the rescue and recovery process, Joseph witnessed people come from the Chicago Fire Department and other places around the country to help out. Joseph worked on the bucket brigade on “The Pile.” These events and experiences of 9/11 changed him. He became more alert and emotional because of the sights and smells he experienced at Ground Zero. Joseph sometimes shares his stories with other responders because it is easier to talk to cops, fire fighters, and people who have been through similar experiences. Joseph also lost some residents of his hometown on 9/11. Joseph feels that the city has turned its back on his fire patrol since 9/11. After nearly 150 years of operation they shut the patrol down. In his reflections, Joseph believes he would have gone into the building if he had had more training in high rise rescues. He says, in retrospect, “You are always going to have doubts.” He also believes that when the worst happens, “Humanity steps up,” that generally people are good, but sometimes the feeling just does not last long enough.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
  - Glenn oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, March 22, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 116
    Glenn has been a Local 3 Union Electrician for 28 years. He is still working in NYC. On 9/11, Glenn had taken the LIRR to Penn Station and sat with his friend, Ralph. He then took a subway to the downtown area. He was across the highway from the WTC working in a building on the 20th floor at the time of the attacks. At 8:45 AM he heard a giant noise and saw two carpenters jumped from a scaffold. He looked down to the street and described it as “unrecognizable with lots of paper flying around.” He recalled being at the WTC for the first bombing when he was having lunch and his chair came off the ground. He was working with about 100 men, and they all evacuated the building. When he got to the street, the sights were overwhelming--people jumping to their death and crawling from the debris. He headed to the highway and saw body parts everywhere. He could not comprehend what he was seeing. He heard an extremely loud sound – the second plane hitting. He both saw and felt the fireball one block away. He felt the heat and saw terror he will never forget on an Asian girl’s face. He went into survival mode; he thought more planes were coming. He and his partner headed toward the Hudson River in an attempt to get to Penn Station. A police officer tried to prevent him and he pushed him out of the way. He wanted to go north and fought his way through throngs of people. He thought of jumping in the river to escape. He was amazed at the amount of women’s shoes in the streets—100s of them and laptops scattered about. He saw the hole in the north tower. He worked his way north and saw a fellow electrician, a woman, crying. He grabbed her and got on a bus. Glenn recalled that he was supposed to be on the 99th floor of the WTC on 9/11, until a last minute change in his work schedule. He finally reached Penn Station and said it was like WWII. It was dead silent and surreal—people were standing around listening to car radios. F-16s were flying overhead. He could not get home because Penn Station was closed. Four hours later, it reopened and he was able to get a train to Long Island. He fell apart when he got home. For days he watched the events unfold on TV. He discovered his friend, Ralph, who he travelled with each day on the LIRR, had been killed. He lost a total of eight friends on 9/11. He feels fortunate to have survived but later became very angry. Glenn went back to work the following Monday--a few blocks from Ground Zero putting microwave dishes on the top of a building. Debris covered the top of the building. He was shocked that his company sent him back to the area. He was sent to Ground Zero to pick up other electricians’ tools. The smell was horrendous—“the smell of construction and death.” He worked for a few days in the downtown area and then did not return until February. The pile of debris had lessened, but there were electrical cables all over the ground—it was dangerous. Oil tanks and generators were everywhere. In February, he was sent to work at the Winter Garden, a building that was mostly glass and was totally destroyed during the attacks. Glenn was happy to be there and help to rebuild. He was there 10 hours a day, 7 days a week. He spoke of amazing people from the Salvation Army with supplies of boots, gloves, food, counseling, etc. His motivation to work in the area was pride and “to do the right thing.” He believes responders risked both their physical and mental health and “we should not be forgotten.” He felt it was more important to help the country than his own health. He said, “A lot of selfless people were down there.” He felt patriotic. Glenn began to have problems about 4-5 years after 9/11. Initially he thought he was over it, but he became very angry until he hit rock bottom. His girlfriend and his children suffered. He feels better now due to counseling, etc., and is now getting back “in the groove.” He feels he has finally dealt with it and is feeling very good lately. He now realizes what is important and has become a very thoughtful person. He believes the event will never be over for any New Yorker and it is still fresh in their minds. There were no positives he gained from his experience and believes we will be attacked again although he has begun to let his guard down a little bit. He still goes to NYC each day and thinks it is not good for him mentally as it causes flashbacks. He feels some Muslims knew of the attacks, and mentioned there were no coffee carts in the area on 9/11 and he saw people celebrating at a mosque in Queens.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Steven Spak oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, March 22, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 117
    Steven was born in the Brooklyn Projects in 1959. At age 19 he obtained a job as an EMS and was stationed permanently at Coney Island Hospital. He went on to become a court officer as well as an EMS. He started taking photographs in 1977 for the department. With this background he volunteered in 1989 for the fire department and started shooting videos for them. Danielle, Steven’s daughter, was born on September 7, 2001, while he was working in the Brooklyn County Court as senior court clerk. The morning of September 11, Steven was at home. Around 9 AM he started hearing about a plane crashing into the tower, so he grabbed his camera equipment and headed to the scene via the Triborough Bridge. He shot many pictures including people watching the scene, the collapse of Building 7 next to the WTC, and the sites adjacent to the World Trade Center. He also took graphic pictures of smoldering fires and smoke spreading across the WTC sites. He mentions the story of Ladder Six being a miracle. Due to the air conditions, he needed his eyes washed out by the treatment center there. As a photographer for the fire department, he witnessed a lot and was able to maintain equilibrium, but this was very traumatic for him. He worried that his wife knew that he was there. Steven’s passion as a child for firefighting grew into an equal passion for his photography as an adult. He returned to the site for more pictures on September 29, 2001. Much work had been done since he had been there, but he still saw fires and smoke rising. He saw boot washing stations and in talking to the workers learned most of them were from FEMA, the FDNY, and the police department. He remarked that “too many were killed for nothing.” The thought of all of those families who were affected by the tragedy motivated him to return to the site this day. By documenting his story, Steven feels that the public will be more understanding of what took place that morning. He feels that the real heroes were those responders who are normally involved in the public services such as firefighters and police officers. Steven now suffers with RADS (reactive airways disease syndrome), sinus infections, and GERD. He also has PTSD which makes him anxious and jumpy. He states “God does things for different reasons we don’t understand why.” He says his life has been divided into two; pre-9/11 and post-9/11.
    - Moving Images
      The "Ground Zero Video" is Mr. Spak's footage of responders working to recover bodies at Ground Zero. Note that the Ground Zero Video has an audio track, but it was damaged in some way prior to acquisition, and is not intelligible.
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Edward Burns oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, March 23, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 118
    Eddie was raised in the projects and later moved to the Bushwick section of Brooklyn. His mother was Puerto Rican and his father was American Indian and Scottish. He attended public schools and many members of his extended family were public servants. When Eddie was younger, he went through a period feeling lost. He didn’t know what he wanted to do with his life. His dad told him to take all the civil service exams he could and see which ones he did well on. He had thought at one time, he would like to be a marine biologist but he ended up being a police officer, like his father. Eddie worked as a foot patrolman for the 83rd precinct. One of the areas he covered was Hope Gardens, an area that his father helped to build. Everyone in the area knew Eddie, and he was very proud to have grown up in the projects and then work in an area where he knew so many people. He felt he was a role model for the younger kids. Eddie was a beat officer for 10 years. On the morning of 9/11, his wife was at school and he was at a local deli with his daughter in Greenpoint. His daughter, who was 4 years old at the time said, “Daddy, look at the plane.” He looked up and saw the belly of the plane overhead. It was the clearest day ever and he could see the towers. He saw the plane heading for the tower and knew something was wrong. The plane disappeared behind a building and just then the 2nd tower exploded. Eddie took his daughter home, and he waited for his wife who was down by 7th avenue at the Swedish School for Massage. She walked over the 59th Street Bridge into Long Island City, before she could find her way home to Greenpoint. Eddie left as soon as she got home and reported for duty. He arrived at the precinct and was given flares, lights, batteries, gloves (no masks), and then he headed to Ground Zero. He was feeling numb and frustrated. Why would anyone do this to us? He drove around and it was like all of Manhattan had been evacuated. Everything was covered in dust; it was eerie, scary, and gloomy, like one of those plague movies. The smell was indescribable. It was a combination of jet fuel and bodies. He was assigned to take away cameras from anyone in the surrounding area who took pictures, whether it was the media or tourists. He rode around the perimeter trying to get closer to the center, but he was nervous. He also patrolled the surrounding areas and said that looting was a problem. The firemen worked really hard and the steelworkers were phenomenal. They had to perform delicate removal of steel beams; cutting and moving them on barges. Things were more organized as time went on. He remembers stopping at a Burger King that was feeding anyone in need. He had a frozen pie in one hand and he was smoking a cigarette in the other. His partners laughed at him. Eddie found no one, dead or alive. At one point he realized that other responders were wearing masks and so he found one. He went back to the precinct that night to clean up and he slept there the first night. The next day he was assigned to assisting the firemen and patrolling the roads. He said the firemen worked very hard. He knew they lost a lot of people. Eddie said he went back every day because he had a sense of duty. He took a sworn oath and he had an obligation to help others. At one point, volunteers were sought after to go to Fresh Kills landfill, so Eddie went. For about 2 months on the weekends he went; suited in a Tyvek suit and mask with his arms and legs duct taped to keep the debris out of the openings. Names of the workers were written into their boots, so they could be identified if anything happened. Cars were hosed down when they left. Cranes would dump debris from barges and then the task would be to sift and if you found anything, put it in the bucket for later identification. The ground was bubbling under him; it was what he expected Mars to be like. Eddie believes that the love of mankind existed on 9/11; that everyone answered the call to duty on that day. He said there was togetherness and camaraderie. The Red Cross and restaurants that stayed open were phenomenal. Eddie believes that people involved in 9/11 used each other for strength and that was inspiring to him. He is happy and proud to have been a part of that. His advice to others is to "Enjoy your life, live righteously and with respect towards others. Always be at your best even when others are at their worst." After 9/11, Eddie left the city and moved to Long Island because he was afraid for his family. In 2006, after putting in his 10 years, he retired. He loves being out east in what he calls "farm country." When he wakes up he sees rabbits and deer and at night he sees the raccoons. He loves music and plays a guitar. He spends his time by the water soaking in life and the nature that surrounds him. For Eddie, this may have been a necessary part of his healing. He lives with his wife and young daughter.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - George Hartig oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, March 29, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 119
    George worked as an elevator mechanic for the NYPD on 9/11. He was working at One Police Plaza within sight of the WTC towers. One Police Plaza served as a communication hub for the NYPD. On the morning of 9/11, he recalled feeling his building shake, and hearing sirens from fire engines and rescue vehicles from all over the place. One Police Plaza later became a triage center for the American Red Cross. It was set up with cots, eyewash stations, and other medical equipment. George was involved in keeping the communication system up and running. His orders to work came from the chief of the department. He worked out a schedule with other staff at the building, and stayed at his post for more than a week at One Police Plaza. He was fitted by NIOSH with a respirator. He worked eight hour shifts. George also did the piping for the electricity to run the power washes, so they could clean up rescue vehicles and radiators covered with fine dust from the debris. He observed that the camaraderie of the workers was “exceptional” and that “no one discussed their paycheck.” While performing his duties, George was motivated most by memory of the people lost in the towers.
    - Moving Images
  - Emanuel D'Andrea oral history interview conducted by Deborah Hawkins, March 31, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 120
    Emanuel was a Verizon field technician on 9/11/2001. Around 9/20/2001 he went down to the site, near Canal Street. He worked in the surrounding buildings, restoring communications. He describes the scene as ‘organized chaos.’ There were various enforcement agencies such as FBI, CIA, Secret Service, and federal marshals that had set up tents in the area. He remembers that everything was covered with dust, and that there was a distinct odor in the area. Trucks would come by at 5-6 A.M. to wash the streets, but otherwise everything was covered with gray mud. He also remembers the cars parked along the West Side Highway were covered with dust from the collapse. Emanuel and his crew stayed at a midtown Manhattan hotel surveying and repairing communications around the WTC area by Vesey Street and Canal Street. They commuted by van to the WTC site. Emanuel remembers checkpoints with law enforcement personnel at every corner. As it was a high security area, Emanuel and his crew had to show identification badges to get near the site. During the first two weeks, they were surveying the area, and Emanuel remembers that no one was allowed by the South Street Seaport area---except them. Emanuel worked at the site from about 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. through mid-October 2001. It was a 24-hour operation. He remembers that he got up at 5:30 am everyday to get to work by the South Street Seaport area, and by the Federal Court Building. He worked primarily on digital and high capacity communication lines. Duty compelled him to return to the site for work every day. He felt that people came together after the WTC attacks and states, “ You have to do what you can do, the best you can do.” Emanuel retired June of 2010 after 40 years of service. He commends the WTC Monitoring Program and feels that people here are very helpful.
    - Moving Images
  - Antonio oral history interview conducted by Deborah Hawkins, March 31, 2011, AFC 2015/048: 121